<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epitomie of mans misery and deliuerie In a sermon preached on the third of the Romans, vers. 23. and 24. By Mr. Paul Bayne.</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 950:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epitomie of mans misery and deliuerie In a sermon preached on the third of the Romans, vers. 23. and 24. By Mr. Paul Bayne.</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kyngston for Nathaniel Newbery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Starre, vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPITOMIE OF MANS MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERY AND DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVERIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON PREACHED ON the third of the Romans, Verſ. 23. and 24. by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL BAYNE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſea 13.9.</bibl>
               <p>O Iſrael, one hath deſtroyed thee; but in me is thine helpe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſaiah 53.6.</bibl>
               <p>All we like ſheepe haue gone aſtray: wee haue turned euery one to his owne way, and the Lord hath laid vpon him the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of vs all.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Starre, vnder Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY BAKER, KNIGHT BAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, health, honour, and happineſſe, from, and in the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, although it bee a complaint (perhaps) not cauſeleſſe, of too many bookes penned and printed in theſe dayes; yet there is, and euer will bee neede of new bookes, chiefly ſuch as ſauour of the wholeſome doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſet forward that knowledge of the truth which is according vnto godlineſſe. Nay ſurely, it is no leſſe worke of Gods prouidence, to ſet open the fountaine of heauenly truth, and to maintaine it in a perpetuall current, by the preaching and writing of his faithfull ſeruants; then that the waters of greater riuers, and leſſer ſprings, doe runne with a continuall ſtreame. For what theſe are to the earth to water it, that it may bee fertile for mens behoofe, and ſerue their bodily wants; the ſame are thoſe to Gods Church to make it fruitfull vnto the Lord, and relieue the ſpirituall want of mens ſoules. Beſides, whereas the muddy and poyſonous wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:1706:3"/> of falſe and hereticall doctrine, of vngodly and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy language (like that<note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 16.3.</note> noyſome bloudy ſea in which no ſoule could liue and breath the life of God, doth dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bubble, or rather puddle forth with proud and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtreames, through the tongues and pens of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels ſcribes, or ſcriblers rather: Is it not a ſingular bleſsing, that the<note n="b" place="margin">Miraris ſi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſapientia omne opus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùm impleuit? Nondum tota ſe nequitia protulit. Senec. nat. quaeſt. lib. 3. c. 32.</note> fountaine of truth doth hold its courſe alſo, from whence iſſue the wholeſome waters of life, to correct the poyſon of the diuels puddle, and preſerue Gods people from the deadly contagion of it? Which wholly to damme vp, or in part to reſtraine, were as great a deſpite vnto Gods people, as was done vnto <hi>Iſaac</hi> by the Philiſtims, in<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 26.15.</note> ſtopping vp all the welles which <hi>Abraham</hi> had digged open. What though in new bookes we bring to light (ſpecially in poynts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) no new matter? who (I pray) doth cauill at it in liuing fountaines, that they run ſtill the ſame waters in colour, kind, and taſt? we doe rather like them ſo much the better, counting it a ſpeciall benefit, that by their perpetuall courſe, as wee haue the ſame waters for kind: ſo we receiue them euer freſh, whereby they are the more pleaſant for taſt, and the more wholeſome for our vſe. So it is a commendation rather than any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections in our new writings, that they propound ſtill the ſame ancient doctrine touching faith, &amp; good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but haply in ſome new forme and method, wherby they giue a freſher and more pleaſant reliſh to theſe wholeſome waters, and ſo quicken mens dull and diuers appetites to the better liking of them, and allure them the more liberally to drinke thereof. I may therefore (I truſt, to good purpoſe) adde alſo this Sermon of that godly and faithfull Preacher Maſter <hi>Paul Bayne,</hi> vnto ſome other books of his, ſet forth by my ſelfe and others,
<pb facs="tcp:1706:3"/> and open (as it were) one little fountaine more, for thirſty ſoules to draw and drinke of. Come to it and taſt who will, I aſſure him that hee ſhall prooue the waters thereof to be good, ſweet, and wholeſome. Among wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wonders<note n="d" place="margin">The French Comment on Bartas, in the third day of his firſt week, out of Mela.</note> writers report of two ſprings, not farre diſtant one from the other in one of the fortunat Ilands; the one whereof doth yeeld deadly waters, and the other very wholeſome: who ſo drinketh of the firſt, is anone taken and torne with moſt painfull conuulſions, euen vnto death; againſt which, the onely ſure and preſent remedy is to drinke of the other fountaine there at hand. This fountaine (which here is opened) riſeth out of Paradiſe (I meane the Scriptures) with one head, but in the courſe thereof it is parted into two ſtreames. The firſt giuing vs the taſt of our ſinfull and damnable ſtate by nature, is very bitter, and in it ſelfe mortall: but the ſecond, refreſhing vs with the knowledge of our redemption by Chriſt, is as the water of life, and wine of Gods loue, moſt cordiall and comfortable. If any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be made whole and ſound in ſoule, he muſt drinke deepe of both. The doctrine of our wretchedneſſe (like vnto the<note n="e" place="margin">Numb. 15.18.</note> bitter and curſed water in the Law) must ſearch how ſound we be within, or rather make vs feele the ſicke and rotten ſtate of our ſoule. And then the doctrine of our ſaluation by Chriſt, like the<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 5.4.</note> waters of Betheſda, must reſtore vs, curing vs of our inward rottenneſſe and outward ſores, whereof wee are deadly ſicke.<note n="g" place="margin">Is corde ſolus arido Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſitit; Sentit miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam corde qui fracto ſuam.</note> We ſhall neuer thirſt heartily, nor reliſh fully the ſweet waters of life in Ieſus Chriſt, vntill we haue drunk deepe of the ſalt and bitter waters of our owne miſery. Nor will they heale or worke vpon our ſoules to health, vntill theſe make our vnſound and rotten hearts ſmart euen to death. This fountaine (I grant) is not deepe, and
<pb facs="tcp:1706:4"/> like<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 8.6.</note> Shiloah, doth runne but ſoftly. For it ſerueth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Gods Lambes to wade in, than Elephants to ſwimme in: and it aimeth more to bring men to a feeling of their miſery in themſelues, and true reioycing in their ſaluation by Chriſt, than to exerciſe their heads with curious contemplation of ſchoole-poynts. What it is (as it is no degenerate of-ſpring of a good man and worthy diuine, not wholly vnknowne vnto you, and ſometime entertained by you) I offer it (moſt worthy Sir) vnto your worſhips hands. Entertaine it (I pray you) according to your wonted and natiue cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, a vertue (in the eyes of all) eminent in you, and which (in a ſpeciall degree) is appropriate vnto your ſelfe: and deriue ſome part of that loue and kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to this orphane Sermon, which ſometime you did ſhew vnto the author of it in his life.</p>
            <p>For my part, I haue ſent it abroad with your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips name wreathed, ſo to ſpeake, on the fore-front thereof; that whereſoeuer it doth paſſe, it may report your ſingular kindneſſe and good will many waies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and yet continued toward me, and ſtand vp as a witneſſe of my thankfull remembrance and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the ſame. An office which (I hope) will not be vngratefull vnto you: who although you are farre from<note n="i" place="margin">Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles vt Cicero in orat: pro Archia.</note> his mind which counted that voice the ſweeteſt muſicke which did moſt loudly chaunt his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, yet may (without impeachment of your modeſty) heare this imperfect Eccho of them, from my ruder tongue, rather ſtammering thankes from an honeſt heart, than glozing with you by a lauiſh blazing of of your praiſe.</p>
            <p>But not to hold you longer from the Sermon it ſelfe, by my courſer manner of diſcourſing, proceed (Good
<pb facs="tcp:1706:4"/> Sir) to loue and countenance learning and vertue; mor ſpecially, foſter piety and religion, hang out from your houſe (as from an high watch-tower) a banner thereof for example and encouragement to all that feare God. Eſteeme vertue the noblest armes of Gentry: as not amiſſe the Heathen<note n="k" place="margin">Iuuenal. Satyr. 8.</note> Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Nobilitas ſola eſt atque vnica virtus.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Vertue is onely</l>
                  <l>True Nobility.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And religion the honour and crowne of Nobility, as better the<note n="l" place="margin">Prudent. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre.</note> Chriſtian Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Generoſa Chriſti ſecta nobilitat viros:</l>
                  <l>Cui quiſque ſeruit, ille vere eſt nobilis:</l>
                  <l>Illi rebellis inuenitur degener.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The generous faith of Chriſts profeſſion,</l>
                  <l>Doth men ennoble with the beſt renowne:</l>
                  <l>Who him doth ſerue comes of the nobleſt blood,</l>
                  <l>Who him reiects, much baſer is than mud.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And in all this take in good part my well meaning heart, who for this, or whatſoeuer ſeruice I can doe, haue the full price of my labour to be reputed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue in the Lord, I. E.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:5"/>
            <head>AN EPITOMIE OF MANS MISERIE AND DELIVERIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 3. verſ. 23.24.</bibl>
                  <p>All haue ſinned, and are depriued of the glory of God, and are iuſtified freely by his grace, thorow the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two things very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for euery Chriſtian:<note place="margin" type="runsum">Two things are needfull to be knowne.</note> the one is the knowledge of our ſelues; the other is the knowledge of the things that concerne our peace. For the firſt, if we bee ſinners, that is, ſuch as feele the burthen of ſinne,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our miſerie.</note> and perceiue our ſelues ſicke thereof: then Chriſt Ieſus is ſent to call vs, then he is a phyſician to vs, Mark. 2.17. For the ſecond, Luk. 19.42. our Sauiour (in moſt tender compaſſion) doth wiſh vnto Ieruſalem but this one thing,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our deliuery.</note> as that which would make her perfectly h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppy, namely, that at leaſt ſhe had knowne (in that her day) thoſe things which belonged to her peace; intimating thus much, that heerein conſiſteth true
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1706:6"/> happineſſe. Now though nothing is more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs than the knowledge of theſe things, yet few things are more neglected. This therefore hath giuen me occaſion to ſpeake and diſcourſe of theſe words, wherein both theſe poynts are ſufficiently taught and declared; that ſome who haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been ſtrangers in them, may bee better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith; others who haue ſet foot in theſe waies may be holpen forward.</p>
            <p>But that we may haue the more conuenient paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the profitable handling of theſe words, it is meet that their coherence bee ſhewed, and that what is more difficult in them be vnfolded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runsum">The coherence of the text.</note>The Apoſtle in them doth make a digreſſion for the preuenting of an obiection which ſome Iew might make againſt his former concluſion. For the Apoſtle (in the verſe going before) thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, that all are iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of faith; ſome Iew (in regard of the ſingular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminences which they had aboue other (of which in the ninth of this Epiſtle wee may reade) might ſtomack the matter, and take it hainouſly, that they are thruſt into the ſelfeſame order with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed Gentiles. Wherefore the Apoſtle (to cure all heart-burning in this behalfe) doth in this verſe (by way of preuention) proue the vniuerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his concluſion from equall condition of all, in the contrary thus: All are ſinfull and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, therefore all, both Iew and Gentile, haue need to be iuſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runsum">The ſenſe: Gods glory is the image of God.</note>In the former words there is no obſcurity: the latter phraſe of being depriued of Gods glory is ſomewhat intricate: ſome taking it to ſignifie the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1706:6"/> image of God: but then leſſe ſhould bee ſpoken than was before; yea and that with leſſe perſpicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; others for glorying or reioycing before God: but this meaning the words will not beare, but by violence and conſtraint.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Or rather, the glorius preſence of God.</note> I rather thinke the true meaning to be, that all men come ſhort, and are depriued of the glory of God, that is, the glorious eſtate wherein the righteous ſhould haue liued for euer, enioying the preſence of God. So Pſal. 73.24. <hi>Thou ſhalt guide me by thy counſell, and afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me to glory.</hi> And the eſtate which the godly ſhal enioy after the labours of this life outwraſtled, is called the ſtate of glory, becauſe the glory of God in the glorifying of his creature, ſhall bee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and eſpecially reuealed. So then the ſum of theſe words is this: All men haue ſinned, all men by nature haue no part of euerlaſting life, but are condemned and adiudged to eternall darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 1.</head>
               <p>The firſt inſtruction which wee muſt heere take vp, is this; that all men by nature are ſinfull,<note place="margin" type="runsum">All men are by nature ſinfull.</note> and ſtand before the tribunall ſeat of God guilty ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. All of vs (as the Prophet ſpeaketh, Iſa. 53.6.) haue turned aſide from our childhood like ſtray ſheepe, to thoſe waies which are abomination to God, dangerous, yea deadly to our ſelues. To which purpoſe, Gen. 8.21. the Lord thus ſpeaketh, that the imagination of mans heart is onely euill euen from his youth vp. And <hi>Dauid</hi> confeſſeth of himſelfe that he was conceiued in ſinne, and borne in iniquitie, Pſalm. 51. Neither can it bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for all of vs came out of <hi>Adams</hi> loynes,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Becauſe they deſcend from ſinfull Adam.</note> and by <hi>Adam</hi> muſt needs be begotten in his image, as it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1706:7"/> is ſpoken, Geneſ. 5.3. that is, not onely reſembling him in creation, but in corruption. Vpon which ground <hi>Iob.</hi> (chap. 14. verſ. 4.) asketh who it is that can bring a cleane thing out of filthineſſe? him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe making anſwere thereunto, that there is none can doe it, it is impoſſible to be done. I will not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour further to proue this poynt: for no man but (generally) doth (very contentedly) acknowledge it. I will onely ſhew the ſame doctrine in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">We are ſinners in three reſpects.</note>Euery man therefore is a ſinner before God in three reſpects: firſt, in regard of ſinne imputed to him: ſecondly, in conſideration of ſinne inherent in him: thirdly, by reaſon of ſinne iſſuing from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>1.</hi> By the ſinne of Adam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to vs.</note>Firſt (I ſay) all of vs are ſinners before God, in reſpect of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt ſinne, which (after a ſort) appertaineth to vs, and is truly ours. All fleſh when <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, did likewiſe with him rebelliouſly tranſgreſſe. For which cauſe the Apoſtle, Rom. 5.12. ſaith, that in him, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Adam</hi> wee haue all ſinned. For <hi>Adam</hi> being the root of all mankinde, we were in him,<note place="margin" type="runsum">In whom wee were, and ſinned.</note> and in time, to ſprout and ſhoot out of him: he being our firſt parent, wee were in his loynes, and lineally to deſcend from him: and ſo as <hi>Leui</hi> (in the ſeuenth to the Hebrewes, 9.10.) is ſaid to pay tithe vnto <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> becauſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> (from whom <hi>Leui</hi> did ſpring in the third generation) yeelded that duty: ſo all of vs being in the loynes of <hi>Adam</hi> (the Lord ſo decreeing it) whatſoeuer he did, that was likewiſe to bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as our deed.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Whoſe ſinne is therefore iuſtly charged on vs.</note> Neither is it vniuſt with God to charge the perſonall deed of one, on the heads of vs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1706:7"/> all. For we ſee in the iuſt proceedings of Princes the ſame reſembled: who hold guilty, not the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor only, but the whole blood, race, or lineage thus tainted, who are therefore iuſtly diſ-inherited. And thus much ſhall ſuffice touching the firſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>2.</hi> By ſinne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in vs.</note> we are all ſinners in the eye of God in regard of ſinne, which (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) dwelleth in vs. And this is nothing elſe but the lacke of righteouſneſſe which originally was in man, and a ſpirituall leproſie of iniquitie, whereby all his powers inward and outward are infected: but this poynt I will explaine more manifeſtly. There was in man not onely a naturall, but a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, which the Apoſtle calleth the life of God,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.18.</note> conſiſting of a ſingular knowledge in the minde,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Lacking due righteouſneſſe.</note> ſtraightneſſe (as <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſpeaketh, chap. 7.31.) or righteouſneſſe in the will, holineſſe in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But now man hath no light in his mind; as in the eleuenth verſe of this Chapter our author ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out of the 14. and 53. Pſalmes:<note place="margin" type="runsum">In the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> 
                  <hi>no man vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth,</hi> that is, no man but by nature hee is quite ſtripped of all vnderſtanding in things ſpirituall and heauenly: the inward eye lacketh that ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which clothing the will (after a ſort) ſhould make it to moue after things which are truly good. In the place aboue named, the Apoſtle addeth,<note place="margin" type="runsum">In the will.</note> None ſeeketh or enquireth after God, that is, the will hath no power whereby it ſhould moue after God, and ſo by conſequent any thing that is truly good. For as to diſallow or approue are functions of the vnderſtanding; ſo to eſchew or proſecute, are faculties appertaining to the will.</p>
               <p>So in the third place,<note place="margin" type="runsum">In our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> all the affections want
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1706:8"/> that holineſſe that ſhould cauſe their motions to be ſanctified, and in ſtead of theſe excellent graces wherewith we were enriched,<note place="margin" type="runsum">And being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and prone to ill.</note> corruption and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe haue made ſeizure of vs, and doe occupie vs thorowout.<note place="margin" type="runsum">In our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> For in our vnderſtanding darkneſſe is ſeated, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the Epheſians, chap. 5. verſ. 8. that before their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion (whileſt yet they abode in their naturall condition) they were darkneſſe it ſelfe: hauing (as it is chap. 4. verſ. 18. their cogitations darkened, ſo that not the leaſt ſparke of ſpiritual light did ſhine in them: yea manifold atheiſticall doubtings and wauerings, touching God, his truth, iuſtice and goodneſſe are moſt manifeſt and frequent in vs, and euen poſſeſſe vs: than the which there is not a more pregnant proofe of our groſſe ignorance in things diuine. For how could we doubt of theſe things, if with a cleare eye of vnderſtanding we did ſee them? Doubting, howſoeuer occaſionally it be a mother of knowledge, yet in it ſelfe it is the fruit &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ignorance.<note place="margin" type="runsum">In our will.</note> The will is altogether rebellious, as the Apoſtle further ſaith, All are gone out of the way. The word, Pſalm. 14.3. ſignifieth to giue backe ſturdily, as a ſtubburne heifer that refuſeth to admit the yoke: implying thus much, that the will of man is become croſſe and ouerthwart, neither is, nor can bee ſubiect vnto any thing that is good. Take an experiment heereof in our ſelues. From this rebellion of the will it commeth to paſſe, that our wicked willes, the more they are vrged with the righteous commandement of God, the more our vileneſſe and filthineſſe breaketh out and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected.<note place="margin" type="runsum">In our deſires and affections.</note> So for our luſts and deſires, Gal. 5.17.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1706:8"/> they are againſt the ſpirit, that is, againſt that law of righteouſneſſe which the ſpirit (as the finger of God) doth write in our hearts. Our ioy, our feare, our hope, our loue, theſe are impurely and vnholily moued in vs, being carried after euill and vnlawfull obiects, or not contained with in due limits for the manner and meaſure of them. You will aske how I can tell that man is thus void of all righteouſnes, and couered with corruption.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our corruption is diſcouered. <hi>1.</hi> From the Law.</note> To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, this may be knowne by the Law. In the 20. verſe of this Chapter it is ſaid, that by the Law doth come the knowledge of ſinne, not onely of that which paſſeth from vs in ſome act, but of that which is ſtill reſident within vs. For whatſoeuer righteouſneſſe the Law requireth, it doth preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in man an excellent conformity, and inward grace ſutable and agreeable thereunto. For the Lord could not in iuſtice haue required that of his creature, which his creature was neuer inabled to performe.</p>
               <p>Now if we lay our ſelues vnto the Law,<note place="margin" type="runsum">To which wee neither doe, nor can conforme.</note> we ſhall finde that there is nothing in man that doth, or can moue him to fulfill the righteouſneſſe of it: nay, that that which is in him doth draw him back as which is not, neither indeed can be ſubiect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>2.</hi> By our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> whoſoeuer are become new men in Chriſt Ieſus may hence perceiue it. For this is a maxime in diuinity, that whatſoeuer is recouered and found of vs in Chriſt, was firſt loſt in <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">Wherein what good we receiue, was before it wanting in vs.</note> Finde you then, that ſince you came to dwell by faith in Chriſt, and he in you, you haue receiued to know God your heauenly Father? know, that by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1706:9"/> nature this knowledge was cleane gone. Perceiue you, that knowing the Father you come to this, that you can truſt in him for helpe in trouble, and a ſupply of all good both bodily and ſpirituall? vnderſtand then, that by nature there was no ſuch confidence toward God in you. Come you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the knowledge of God your Father, to loue him, his word, and thoſe that are begotten of him? Come you to delight and reioyce in theſe? perſwade your ſelfe that by nature you were vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of this ſpirituall loue and ioy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> By the ſtrife of the fleſh and ſpirit, in which the fleſh wholly is oppoſite to the ſpirit.</note>Thirdly, if thou be a regenerate man, thou maiſt diſcerne it by the ſtrife of the fleſh and ſpirit in thee. In the which obſerue if thou canſt finde any good in thy fleſh. Is there any knowledge in it? Nay, doe not rather the reliques of the fleſh that are in thee, make the word of God (which is in it ſelfe moſt cleare) darkſome and obſcure? Is there any obedience in it? nothing leſſe. The law of the members ſtill rebelleth againſt the law of the mind: ſo that needs wee muſt confeſſe with <hi>Paul,</hi> that in vs, that is, in our fleſh, in our ſtate of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dwelleth no good, Rom. 7.18. To apply this to our purpoſe: marke, what the fleſh is, that are we altogether by nature: for we come to be ſpirit, not by carnall generation, but by ſpirituall regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this leauen of vncleanneſſe hath crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the outward members, that the eyes, eares, lips, tongue, hands, feet, are euery where in the Scripture branded for weapons of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And ſo let vs paſſe vnto the third conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> By actuall tranſgreſſion.</note>In the third place, wee are ſinners in regard of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1706:9"/> actuall tranſgreſſions. you haue often heard of ſins of omiſſion, and ſinnes of commiſſion.<note place="margin" type="runsum">In ſinnes of omiſſion.</note> It is worth the marking to ſee whence theſe kindes ariſe: for when we are altogether depriued of righteouſnes, it cannot be but that wee ſhould omit and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe whatſoeuer is righteous. For where the cauſe is not, nor euer was, there the effect muſt needs be wanting. So on the other ſide, when the pollution of ſinne doth wholly occupie the faculties of our mind, ſoule and body, whatſoeuer we thinke, ſpeak,<note place="margin" type="runsum">And of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note> or doe, it cannot but be ſinfull. For ſuch as the tree is, ſuch muſt be the fruit. Neither can figs be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered on thornes, nor grapes on thiſtles. Of which our actuall corruption the Scripture euery where, and ſpecially very plainly doth accuſe man, Pſalm. 14.1. They haue corrupted their waies, and done abomination; there is none that doth good. What is here meant, but that the whole way of a naturall man, the trade of his life is to worke ſuch things as are abomination, and that whatſoeuer is truly good, that he altogether pretermitteth. But this (me thinketh) ſticketh on the ſtomacke, and is not ſo eaſie of digeſtion as the former. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> For you will haply ſay that you haue the knowledge of God, that you can heare Gods word,<note place="margin" type="runsum">The good which we haue by nature</note> that you can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a zeale of ſome kind of righteouſneſſe, that you can pray, giue almes, and doe many other good things, and why then ſhould you be charged with doing no good? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                  </label> But wee muſt bee as wiſe in heauenly things as wee are in earthly: In other matters touching goodly appearances wee can giue this iudgement,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Is but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</note> that all is not gold which gliſters: and ſhould not wee be as carefull, that in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1706:10"/> things ſpirituall we be not deluded with ſhewes in ſtead of ſubſtance? Our Sauiour hath an heauenly ſpeech concerning theſe glittering and ſhining ſinnes (as one doth truly terme them) that what is excellent and glorious oft with men, the ſame is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination in the ſight of God: Luk. 16.15. You may thinke that you know God,<note place="margin" type="runsum">But not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and ſauing.</note> but by nature you haue not, nor can haue any true ſpirituall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him. For as it is 1. Cor. 2.14. The naturall man is not capable of the things of God. Onely bleare-eyed as we are, and ſeeing at hand, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, 2. Pet. 1.9. we can (after a ſort) reade and conceiue what the great bookes of heauen and earth teach vs concerning him; namely, that there is a diuine power, whoſe iuſtice, power, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth not obſcurely manifeſt it ſelfe in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the world. And this knowledge ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in no other ſtead, but onely to make vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable before God. So wee can lend a bodily eare vnto Gods word; but with the eare of the mind we cannot heare: which our Sauiour meanes when he ſaith (to them which heard well enough in reſpect of the bodily ſenſe) <hi>Hee that hath eares to heare, let him heare,</hi> Matth. 13.9. So we may receiue a kind of zeale after good; but it is like that of the Iewes, Rom. 10.2. a wrong zeale, in a wrong man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which leadeth from Chriſt, with whom onely is ſaluation. Wee can alſo giue almes, and doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good works in our owne conceit, and of other men, but in ſuch a manner as that we cannot ſtirre an haires breadth from ſinne,<note place="margin" type="runsum">For want of a cleere fountaine, <hi>viz.</hi> a pure heart.</note> nor get out of the mire wherein wee ſticke. For the Law requireth, not onely that the ſubſtance of the outward worke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1706:10"/> be conformable thereunto, but that the fountaine whence it ſpringeth be pure, Tit. 1.15.<note place="margin" type="runsum">And a right end, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods glory.</note> that the end for which it is vndertaken (whatſoeuer it be) bee the glory of God, 1. Cor. 10.31. Now to haue a hart purified by faith, is not ſuch a vulgar thing that all men haue it: for all men haue not faith, 2. Theſ. 3.2 but theſe onely to whom it belongeth, to whom it is giuen. Phil. 1.29. To you it is freely giuen for Chriſt, that not onely yee ſhould beleeue in him, but alſo ſuffer for his ſake. Wherefore when the Scripture doth pronounce, that whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne, Rom. 4.24. and that without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, Heb. 11.6. let vs not think our pennie made worſe ſiluer than it is, when all our workes that are done in our naturall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are made ſins before God, and ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is highly diſpleaſed, be they neuer ſo good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and beautifull in the ſight of man. The vſe of this doctrine ſhall be ioyntly handled with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther following: wherefore we will paſſe to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond doctrine touching our miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And come ſhort]</hi> That is, are out of the reach and hope of euerlaſting life, and ſo by conſequent are plunged ouer head and eares into eternall death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 2.</head>
               <p>From hence then this is our leſſon, that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we haue no part nor portion in that glorious life,<note place="margin" type="runsum">We by nature haue no ſhare in life euerlaſting.</note> and that euerlaſting happineſſe wherewith the preſence of Gods glory repleniſheth his for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, mark what followed thereupon,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.23.</note> hee was ſecluded and caſt out of the earthly Paradiſe: in which the eſtate of vs al is pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed out, and liuely repreſented; namely, that we (being ſinners) are exiled and baniſhed from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1706:11"/> the Paradiſe of God, hauing no intereſt in that glorious inheritance.<note place="margin" type="runsum">But are vnder wrath.</note> Wherefore it is that our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, Epheſ. 2.3. that we are the children of wrath, that is, ſuch as to whom appertaine thoſe puniſhments which the Lord inflicteth in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and not that life of glory which hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to thoſe with whom he is well pleaſed.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Becauſe ſinfull wretches.</note> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it poſſibly bee otherwiſe with vs: for the wages of ſinne is death, the iuſtice of God ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, Rom. 6.23. What other pay then can wee challenge or expect, but that of eternall death, who are euery way moſt ſinfull wretches, as wee haue already heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">Whom heauen cannot admit.</note>Againe, the heauenly Ieruſalem is a place ſo pure, that no vncleane thing, nothing that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any abomination, may haue any doings there, Reuel. 21. There is then no place for vs therein, who are ſo beſmeared and ſtained with ſinne, that whatſoeuer wee turne our ſelues vnto, is (before the Lord) no better than abomination. And this in generall may ſuffice touching this doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">For we are dead. <hi>1.</hi> Here ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually.</note>But now for as much as wee are not (as ſoone as we come forth of the wombe) caſt into hell: know therefore that euery one of vs are firſt come ſhort of this glory in regard of ſpirituall and heauenly life: of the which there is not by nature the leaſt ſparke remaining in vs, we being ſtarke dead in our ſinnes: as (often) the Scripture expreſly ſpeaketh, Epheſ. 2.1. You were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes. and Mat. 8.22. Let the dead bury their dead. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men then who are void of this ſpirituall life, are no better (in the Lords account) than dead men, who when they burie others dead as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1706:11"/> this bodily life, it is as pretty a pageant, as to ſee one dead corps carry or accompany another vnto the graue. Yea, let men frolick it, and ruffle in pleaſures, and not onely liue in their conceits, but liue brauely and deliciouſly; yet euen in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they are but dead; and the more thus they liue, the further are they plunged into death, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1. Tim. 5.6. of the widow,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our naturall life being but a ſhadow of life.</note> that ſhee that liueth in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liueth. It is but a conceit, a name of life, that naturall men haue: it is but a goodly vizour drawne ouer a dead and rotten corps. Thou haſt a name that thou liueſt, but thou art dead, ſaith our Sauiour to the Angell of Sardi, Reuel. 3.1. Notwithſtanding heere the Lord doth let his Sunne to ſhine, and his raine to fall on the vngodly, together with his owne; and theſe dead ſoules enioy many documents of Gods fauour and bounty; whereby they neither ſeeme, nor indeed are, ſo wholly and vtterly ſeparate from happineſſe as they ſhall bee.<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Subiect to the bodily death</note> Wherefore there is a ſecond ſtaire, by which all of vs (if the Lord ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour not) deſcend yet further from this bleſſed life, and this glorious conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is in death, when a diſſolution of ſoule and body commeth. Then the body is committed to the earth, where it feeleth no good at all, as in life it did, nor any euill: and the ſoule is gathered to the ſpirits of apoſtate angels, and reſerued to eternall condemnation in chaines of darkneſſe, Iude 6. Laſtly,<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> To death eternall.</note> there is yet one lower deſcent, in the day of iudgement, when as ſoule and body at the reſurrection (which is both of iuſt and vniuſt) being reunited, ſhall be ſeparated for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more from the preſence of the Lord, and from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1706:12"/> glory of his power, 2. Theſ. 1.9. and ſhall be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnquenchable fier, where the worme of their conſciences ſhall neuer die, but vnceſſantly vexe and torment them for euer. And ſo we will in one handle the vſes which are to be made of both theſe inſtructions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt then, we are to treaſure vp theſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our hearts,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Is to furniſh vs with matter of confeſſion in our prayers.</note> that they may ſerue vs from weeke to weeke, and from day to day, to direct vs in our prayers for the confeſſion of our ſinnes: wee haue all by rote, and can vtter the words of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> though otherwiſe than hee ſpeaketh them: <hi>In many things we ſinne all,</hi> Iam. 3.2. But rare is that man that truly vnderſtandeth what it is hee vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: wherefore let theſe things be ſtill preſent with vs, that we may vnderſtand fully, and explicate in particular our corruption and miſery,<note place="margin" type="runsum">To doe it feeling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly.</note> when wee come before the Lord to make our confeſſions and prayers. For to confeſſe our ſelues ſinfull and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, &amp; not know how, &amp; wherin we are ſo; ſurely is nothing elſe, but with thoſe wicked Iewes (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord complaineth,<note place="margin" type="runsum">For ſlight and generall confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</note> Iſa. 29.) to draw neere to him with our lips, while our hearts are far from him, and to commit that, from which <hi>Salomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth, Eccleſ. 4.17. <hi>viz.</hi> To offer vp the ſacrifice of fooles, babling with our tongues, what we mind not,<note place="margin" type="runsum">And a mocking of God.</note> or vnderſtand not. Nay, it is a plaine mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God vnto his face, thus (without knowledge and conſciouſneſſe of our ſinfulneſſe in particular, and the ſeuerall branches of it) to confeſſe our ſins. Who would not take himſelfe abuſed by ſuch a debtor? that ſhould confeſſe that he were indebted to him, if he knew for what, but therein hee muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1706:12"/> pardon him. For he could not call to mind where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor why, nor how he ſhould owe him any thing. Such a flouting confeſſion doe we make to God of our ſinnes, when in generall termes wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them, but in the meane while our heart doth not ſmite vs for any in particular, nor can wee tell wherein we are ſo ſinfull. Wee muſt then bee well acquainted with this our miſerable condition: the knowledge whereof will helpe much to enlarge and excite our hearts to a feeling confeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and a more earneſt crauing of Gods mercy for the cure of it. And to driue it home vnto our harts,<note place="margin" type="runsum">To remedie which, we muſt conſider our ſtate in ſinne.</note> when we confeſſe that we are thus tainted in ſoule and body with the leproſie of ſinne: let vs ſeriouſly conſider that we are in a moſt fearfull and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table eſtate.<note place="margin" type="runsum">To be fearfull and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> It is a fearful thing to haue a noyſome diſeaſe, a ſtinking or running ſore on any part of the body: but how much more lothſome and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is it to be couered with boyles and ſcabs, as was <hi>Iob,</hi> and to haue nothing ſound in the whole body: but (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) from the ſole of the foot, to the crowne of the head, to bee laden with wounds, and ſwellings, and ſoares full of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Such a lamentable ſight ſhould we ſee in this ougly leproſie of ſinne wherewith wee are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, if we could diſcerne it: whoſe poyſon and contagion goeth beyond the moſt fearfull and noyſome diſeaſes of the body.<note place="margin" type="runsum">And moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious.</note> For be a diſeaſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, it is (and not without cauſe) terrible; yet cannot it infect where it toucheth not: but a peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, oh how dreadfull is that accounted! what running and flying from it is there? which can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yet infect the aire, and neere and neighbour pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1706:13"/> to the hazard of ſuch as dwell at hand, and thereabouts. But this plague of ſinne hath wrought vpon the whole creature, to infect the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and make all things ſubiect vnto vanity, that as the garment and houſe which were infected in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curably with the leproſie, the one was to bee bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with fier, the other razed downe and carried away, Leuit. 13. and 14. ſo the whole frame of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth muſt burne in the fier to bee purged of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, theſe doctrines are a ground of all true humility,<note place="margin" type="runsum">It teacheth vs humility and thankefulneſſe.</note> and thankfull acknowledgement of Gods mercy. If that a man could haue ſeene the heart of the poore Publican, Luk. 18. no doubt one ſhould haue ſeene, that it was the priuity of theſe things we haue ſpoken of, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was ſo ſinfull and corrupt, ſo wretched and neare to damnation, that made him ſo abaſed and abaſhed in himſelfe, as not to dare ſo much as to looke vp to heauen, made him with ſuch griefe and paſſion to ſmite his breaſt, and to ſigh out, <hi>Lord be mercifull vnto mee a ſinner.</hi> What vvas it but the due pondering of theſe things, that did carry <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſuch an admiration of Gods bounty toward himſelfe and all men, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, Pſal. 144.4. <hi>Lord what is man that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt him? or the ſonne of man that thou thinkeſt on him?</hi> and forceth the Prophet to this confeſſion: <hi>It is the Lords mercy that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſsions faile not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">From the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it ſpringeth pride and vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</note> Lam. 3.22. But contrarivviſe vvee carry our heads aloft, face the heauens, and ſvvell vvith great thoughts of our ovvne vvorth. Againe, vve are not onely ſpared from day to day, and ſaued from vvrath, but are fed and filled vvith
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1706:13"/> good things from Gods hand, without any due and feeling confeſſion of Gods patience, bounty, and mercies heerein. And whence is it but euen hence? that we haue not thorowly learned, nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto heart theſe leſſons, what wee are naturally before God, <hi>viz.</hi> abominable, moſt filthy, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wretches, children of wrath, and ſonnes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Find me the man that doth know this in his ſoule, and is not lowly in his owne eyes; doth not tremble, and is not (with an holy ſhame) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in himſelfe when hee commeth before God, that doth not acknowledge Gods mercy in the leaſt good hee enioyeth, and wonder at his bounty, that he doth load him (ſuch a caitiffe) with ſo great benefits. Grant that poore <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> had been guilty of treaſon againſt King <hi>Dauid,</hi> as <hi>Ziba</hi> did falſly accuſe him; and that vpon plaine conuiction of the crime and ſentence of death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen on him, and all things made ready for his execution, the King had giuen him his pardon, reſtored him to his lands, and (as formerly) admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to his owne table. Can we thinke that hee would not haue bluſhed, euen as oft as he came in the Kings preſence? and that he would not (much more than formerly) haue magnified <hi>Dauids</hi> princely mercy and clemency vnto him, ſaying, What is thy ſeruant that thou ſhouldeſt looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, much more ſhouldeſt deale ſo graciouſly with ſuch a dead dog as I am? 1. King. 9.8. If the apprehenſion of ones outward miſerie and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can ſo abaſe our mindes, and endeare the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies and fauours of other men towards vs: how much rather will it make vs truly humble before
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1706:14"/> the Lord, and thankfully to record his goodneſſe, to vnderſtand well how vile and wretched our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall condition is?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this muſt awake vs to looke about, and lay hold of the meanes of our ſaluation that wee eſcape death and damnation.<note place="margin" type="runsum">It ſhould ſtirre vs vp to lay hold of ſaluation.</note> When the Iewes had heard <hi>Peter</hi> preaching roundly to them concerning their wickedneſſe in crucifying the Lord Ieſus, and their danger for it; they were pricked in their hearts, and cried out to the Apoſtle, <hi>Men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, what ſhall we doe?</hi> Act. 2.37. And truly it muſt needs affright vs, and make vs to labour for a better eſtate, vnleſſe we be of that ſort of men that haue made a couenant with hell, and are at a league with the graue, Iſa. 28.15. to conſider, that we are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before the Lord in the loynes of <hi>Adam:</hi> to weigh that we are throughout ſtained and ſpotted with the filthineſſe of ſinne: to thinke that all we can ſpeake or doe, all our thoughts, words and deeds, are ſo many inditements againſt vs, and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences that wee are ſhut out of heauen into vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkneſſe. Will any man (vnleſſe hee be dead drunke) lay himſelfe downe to ſleepe in the top of the maſt, the ſhip being vnder ſaile in the middeſt of the ſea? Prou. 23.34. And wee hold him deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately mad that dare take a nap in a houſe on fier ouer his head. O then let vs not, when the wrath of God, which is a fier burning to the pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: when (I ſay) this wrath is ſeated in ſoule and body, let vs not preſume to ſnort ſecurely, till we know our ſelues pulled out of this fier, and till we perceiue that it is fully quenched and extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. And thus much ſpoken concerning our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1706:14"/> wretched eſtate by nature were enough. But leſt thoſe who are deliuered from this miſery, ſhould thinke that this doctrine concerneth them not; it ſhall be needfull (in a word) to adioyne one other inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Marke therefore (beloued) who it is that vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe words, <hi>all haue ſinned.</hi> It is <hi>Paul,</hi> one who had now laboured 20. yeeres in the worthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Apoſtleſhip; yet hee ſpeaketh this, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe in the ſame number. Which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs thus much:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 3.</head>
               <p>That after our deliuerance wee muſt not ſhake hands with the doctrine of our miſerie,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our miſerie muſt not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, though wee be deliuered from it.</note> but ſtill beare it in mind, and often recount it. It is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> almoſt euery where. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to the Epheſians, verſ. 3. after he had laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of the Epheſians their former eſtate, he ſpareth not to rip vp his owne conſtitution by nature, thus: <hi>Among whom wee alſo haue had our conuerſation in time paſt, in the luſts of our fleſh, in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the will of the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by nature the children of wrath as well as others.</hi> So again, 1. Tim. 1.15. doth hee ranke himſelfe amongſt the chiefe ſinners: <hi>Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners, whereof I am the chiefe.</hi> Laſtly, Tit. 3.3. doth he make a large acknowledgement of his owne, and others wretched condition, what it was before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: <hi>We our ſelues alſo were in times paſt vnwiſe, diſobedient, deceiued, ſeruing the luſts and diuers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, liuing in maliciouſneſſe and enuie, hatefull, and hating one another.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Effects of its remembrance.</note> And this leſſon is the worthier our learning, by how much the vſe of it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for it hath three excellent effects.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1706:15"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>1.</hi> To make vs gentle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward others.</note>Firſt, to remember what we our ſelues haue bin, and are by nature, will make vs meeke and gentle towards others, not ouer raſh and rigorous in our cenſures. Thus much the Apoſtle ſheweth plainly vnto vs in the place aboue-named. For in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe of that chapter, he doth bid <hi>Titus</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort men from ſpeaking euill, and exhort them to ſoftneſſe and meekneſſe. But now, what reaſon doth he giue why ſuch kindneſſe and courteſie ſhould be vſed toward others? Marke that in this 3. verſe, <hi>for we our ſelues</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were in times paſt diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, vnwiſe, &amp;c.</hi> plainly ſhewing, that nothing more engendreth mildnes and gentlenes toward others, than to ſet before vs what we our ſelues haue been.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>2.</hi> To long for our diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Secondly, in the relicks of ſinne to remember our miſerie, will make vs ſigh and grone for our heauenly tabernacle, and deſire to be diſſolued and to be with Chriſt. As <hi>Dauid</hi> being very much a-thirſt, did long to drinke, and ſaid, <hi>Oh that one would giue me of the water of the well of Bethlehem,</hi> 2. Sa. 23. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hauing wel conſidered of his ſlauiſh and irkſome caſe, through ſinne (abiding in him, and continually moleſting) him doth conceiue an earneſt deſire, and breaks out into moſt paſſionate wiſhes of his full deliuery, Rom. 7.24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> To taſt our ſaluation by Chriſt the more pleaſant.</note>Thirdly, it will make vs taſte the benefit of Chriſt more pleaſantly. When did <hi>Paul</hi> come thankfully (as it were) to take the cup of ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus? euen then when he looked vnto it through the body of death. And therefore after his former exclamation, hee annexeth this thankſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1706:15"/> 
                  <hi>I thanke God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And certaine it is that as the Paſchall Lambe did reliſh the beſt, when it was eaten with ſowre herbs: ſo by theſe remembrances (which humble and breake the ſpirit) our ſaluation by Chriſt is made much more comfortable and ſauoury. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> It is then to be blamed in Gods children,<note place="margin" type="runsum">It reproueth thoſe that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to call it to mind.</note> if they doe not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their thoughts in a freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their naturall miſery. there are diuers who being aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from a lowe eſtate to great preferment, forget their baſe parentage, nor will once looke downe to the dung-hill from whence they were raiſed: but what doth enſue in ſuch perſons, but ſtrange pride and inſolencie? out of which they domineere cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly ouer their inferiours; diſdaine and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt their equalles; and (to their ruine at length) ſet at naught him that aduanced them, not acknowledging his former fauours, and thinking that they can now ſit faſt without him.<note place="margin" type="runsum">It is a faireway to ſpirituall pride.</note> Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are in danger of nothing more than of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pride, with the which the diuell (when all other of his traines faile) hopeth to blow them vp, by dazling their eyes with the view of their perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and preſent happineſſe. And to prepare them thereunto, and make way for this ſtratagem, this he doth driue at to make them forget what they were of old, and little to thinke of their former miſerie: to which if he can bring them, then (with eaſe and readily) will ſucceed vncharitable cenſures, and proud diſdain of others inferiour to them in grace; contentious emulations toward thoſe that match them, or goe before them; yea a ſleight eſteeme of Gods mercy and grace whereby they were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1706:16"/> Great aduantage therefore doe they giue the diuell againſt them, who loue not to keep in mind, and humbly to recount their wretched ſtate by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, euen when (through Gods mercy) they bee freed.</p>
               <p>It followeth. <hi>And are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, whom he hath propoſed a reconciliation through faith in his blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euen as the way to Sion was by Sinai; ſo, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wee deſire rather to bee carnally ſecured, than truly comforted, wee muſt paſſe by the diligent view of our moſt wofull plight (wherein by nature wee are enwrapped) to the conſideration of the good things which the Lord hath prepared for them that loue him. Theſe words then vnfolded, will plainly declare what I propounded to ſhew in the ſecond place, <hi>viz.</hi> the very thing which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to our happines. I cannot caſt them more conueniently (for our capacities) than into theſe three members.<note place="margin" type="runsum">The parts.</note> Firſt, that there is reſtitution for all ſorts of men from this miſery, in theſe words, <hi>All are iuſtified.</hi> Secondly, the grounds or cauſes of this reſtitution, and theſe are two: firſt, the mercy of God, in theſe words, <hi>freely by his grace:</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the redemption in Chriſt, whereof hee ſpeaketh thus, <hi>through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Thirdly, the inſtrument whereby theſe are applied to vs, in verſ. 25. <hi>through faith in his blood.</hi> Theſe three poynts we will handle in order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">We are reſtored from this miſery.</note>That there is a reparation of mans lamentable condition, is not neceſſary to diſpute, ſince it is a matter nothing controuerſall. The Apoſtle, Gal.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1706:16"/> 3.22. euidently ſaith, that all are (by the Scripture) concluded vnder ſinne. But why? that they might lie in this condition? Nothing leſſe: but that the promiſe (through the faith of Ieſus Chriſt) ſhould bee giuen to them that beleeue. And it were woe with vs if this caſe were any whit doubtfull. I will therefore (in ſtead of arguing whether there bee a reſtoring yea or nay) ſet downe the order of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. For though this word <hi>Iuſtified,</hi> doe not ſignifie directly euery parcell of our happy eſtate, yet it (being oppoſed to our miſerable eſtate) doth it ſelfe ſignifie ſome part of our deliuerance from it, and by neceſſary conſequence implieth all that concurreth thereunto.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore let vs know,<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>1.</hi> By iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that for man (guilty before the tribunall ſeat of God, for the ſinne hee committed as he was in <hi>Adams</hi> loynes, and many aduerſe ſinnes in his owne perſon) there is iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Whereby God acquitteth vs from ſinne.</note> nothing elſe (as <hi>Paul</hi> euery where vſeth it) but an action of God as iudge of all the world, whereby he doth acquit his creature of whatſoeuer crime might be laid vnto his charge, holding him for iuſt and innocent: yea and according to this iuſtice which he imputeth to him, hee doth moſt graciouſly entreat him,<note place="margin" type="runsum">And accepteth vs to life.</note> by acception to life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. This is the very import of this word, as is gathered by theſe two arguments. Firſt, it is a word iudiciall, as may bee ſeene, 2. Sam. 15.4. <hi>Oh</hi> ſaith <hi>Abſalom) that they would make me a Iudge in the land, that euery one who hath any matter or controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie might come to mee, and I would doe to him iuſtice,</hi> that is, pronounce him quit, cnd cleare him, as his cauſe requireth.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1706:17"/>
               <p>Secondly, the oppoſition requireth the ſame: for condemnation is ſet againſt it as the contrary, Rom. 8.33.34. <hi>It is God that iuſtifieth, who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne?</hi> And this may be conſidered as the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in our reparation, and is preciſely ſignified by the word it ſelfe: which though it be diſtinguiſhed from theſe that follow (otherwiſe a wholeſome forme of words and doctrine cannot be kept) yet it muſt not be ſeparated.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>2</hi> By ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>Secondly, therefore the Lord, whom hee thus iuſtifieth, he ſendeth into their hearts the Spirit of his Sonne, Gal. 4.6. that ſpirit of promiſe, Epheſ. 1.13. I meane that promiſed ſpirit which doth rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate them throughout: ſo that though they were by nature darkneſſe,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Jn all parts.</note> yet they now become light in the Lord, Epheſ. 5.8. though they were rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (ſuch as could not bee ſubiect) yet now they come to delight (at leaſt in the inner man of their mindes) in the Law of God: though their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were prophane and vnſanctified, yet now they are renewed to that image which is in holineſſe; ſo that their ioy is not fixed in outward things, as wiſedome, ſtrength, riches; but in this, that they know the Lord to be their God in Chriſt, Ier. 9.23.24. and that their names are written in heauen, Luk. 10.20. their loue is ſetled on God, their hearts ſpeaking with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalm. 73.25. <hi>What haue I in heauen but thee? and whom in earth in compariſon of thee?</hi> So alſo their feare and hope is turned from the world, and things temporall, vnto God, and matters euerlaſting. And though before what euer they did, was ſinne; yet now they doe thoſe good workes which the Lord hath prepared for them to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1706:17"/> walke in. And thus the life of glory is againe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For this their ſanctification is the beginning of glory; ſo that euen while they are on earth,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Which is a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of glory.</note> they haue euerlaſting life; <hi>He that beleeueth hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life,</hi> Ioh. 3.36. And Rom. 8.23. wee are ſaid to haue here the firſt fruits of the ſpirit. The firſt fruits and the whole lumpe differ not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and kind, but in the meaſure and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. What were the firſt fruits of corne, oliues, or any other fruit of the earth offered to the Lord vnder the Law, but a part, and a prime part of the whole harueſt: and ſo the ſanctifying graces of Gods ſpirit which wee receiue on earth, are parts and beginnings of our glorious life in heauen, from which they differ not in kind, but in meaſure and degree. Now when Gods faithful ones depart,<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> By glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on begun in death.</note> they goe neerer to the fulneſſe of this glory, as whoſe ſoules goe into Paradiſe, as our Sauiour ſpeaketh to the thiefe, Luk. 23.43. and whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are gathered to the ſpirits of iuſt and perfect men in the heauenly Ieruſalem, Heb. 12.23. But at the reſurrection of the iuſt,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Conſummate at the reſurrection.</note> then ſhall this life of glory bee conſummate, their bodies being made conformable to the glorious body of Chriſt Ieſus, Phil. 3.21. the Lord being glorified in his ſaints, &amp; made maruellous in all them that beleeue, 2. Theſ. 1.10. Thus farre then it goeth well, that wee who were condemned perſons, and had our faces coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as being ready to bee carried away to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhould bee iuſtified: that wee who were drie wood, fruitfull onely in the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, ſhould become greene trees planted in the true temple of the God-head Chriſt Ieſus, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1706:18"/> ſo be made to beare good fruit abundantly, euen to abound in euery good worke, that wee finally (who were dead) ſhould liue.</p>
               <p>Now it is ſome comfort for any man labouring of a deſperate diſeaſe, to heare ſay there is cure for it. But come to one whom ſome griefe incurable (as it is reputed) doth hold, and tel him there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for him; as he will be glad to heare it, ſo hee will hardly beleeue it: wherefore he will aske what be the ingredients or ſimples of which that mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine ſhould be made, that by this meanes (the force of theſe well conſidered) he may ſee if it bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to doe the deed yea or no. So in maladies ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, which no power in heauen or earth (but that which can ſubdue all things to it ſelfe) can correct. To ſay there is a ſalue for theſe ſores, is ſomewhat comfortable, but it will not preſently paſſe for currant. You will therefore aske in the firſt place, how this ſhould come to paſſe: for man is full of ſinne, and the Lords eyes are too pure to behold nothing but filthineſſe. When there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing then in him which may moue God, vnleſſe it be to iudgement; how ſhould the Lord come to-reſtore him? very well. Looke on the next words, <hi>We are iuſtified freely by his grace.</hi> Though there bee nothing in vs, yet the Lord of his free grace doth iuſtifie vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 5.</head>
               <p>This then is our leſſon; that the grace of God, that is,<note place="margin" type="runsum">We are iuſtified freely by Gods meere grace.</note> God himſelfe, of himſelfe, in great fauour and riches of mercy, bowing downe to ſuccour his miſerable creature altogether vndeſeruing: God (I ſay) thus meerly mercifull, doth iuſtifie vs. So the Apoſtle teacheth euery where: Tit. 2.11. <hi>The
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1706:18"/> grace of God bringing ſaluation vnto all men hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</hi> So Epheſ. 2.8.9. <hi>We are ſaued by grace, not of workes:</hi> where it is to bee marked, how the meere grace of God (not excited by any workes, but working of its owne accord) hath the whole ſtroke in our ſaluation. For workes are ſecluded from working any whit therein. And although theſe ſpeeches be plaine enough to cleere the poynt, yet loe how it is affirmed more plainly, 2. Timoth. 1.9. <hi>Who hath ſaued vs, and called vs with an holy calling, not according to our workes but according to his owne purpoſe and grace, &amp;c.</hi> Our ſaluation is of grace; and what grace? not ſuch as doth follow vpon any goodneſſe inherent in vs, or works foreſeene which ſhould come from vs; but onely vpon the intent and purpoſe of God within himſelfe. This is a truth which was well knowne in the time of the old Teſtament. <hi>By mercy and truth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> Prou. 16.6.) <hi>iniquitie ſhall bee forgiuen, and by the feare of the Lord men depart from euill.</hi> What mercy and truth is heere meant? what, that of man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man? no ſurely. It cannot bee fitly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, but of Gods meere grace, whereby he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth good things to men, and his fidelity in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming moſt conſtantly what he promiſeth: from which we obtaine this fauour, to get our ſinnes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and pardoned. As the reuerence of Gods Maieſty doth cauſe his children to eſchew euill; ſo his mercy toward them (being in Chriſt a moſt mercifull Father vnto them) doth beſtow on them the pardon of their ſinnes. And what elſe meant the Saints of old, but to aſcribe all to Gods mercy, when they did alwaies make their requeſt to God,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1706:19"/> and craue of him to haue reſpect vnto them, not for their owne ſake, but for his mercies, which laſt for euer, his kindneſſe and goodneſſe, his names ſake, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">That God may haue the glory of our ſaluation.</note>For Gods glory is moſt deare vnto him, neither can he endure therein to haue any partner. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in the buſineſſe of our ſaluation) hee doth ſo worke, that man may haue no matter of reioycing out of God, who doth all this worke in himſelfe, and out of man; that who ſo reioyceth, might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce onely in the Lord, 1. Cor. 1.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This doctrine ſerueth firſt for confutation, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly for conſolation.<note place="margin" type="runsum">It excludeth all concurrence of our workes.</note> If our iuſtification then be of grace, there can be no reliques of holineſſe, nor workes of our owne that concurre thereunto. For beſides that, theſe are oppoſed in the places aboue cited, the Apoſtle maketh this collection very eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, Rom. 11.6. <hi>And if it bee of grace, it is no more of workes, or elſe were grace no more grace.</hi> For theſe two are ſo oppoſite, that like fier and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they expell each the other: and (as ſaith one) <hi>Gratia nullo modo eſt gratia niſi ſit omni modo gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta:</hi> Grace is no way to bee counted grace, vnleſſe euery way it bee moſt free. For this cauſe marke how the Apoſtle ioyneth freeneſſe or frankneſſe, vvith grace. The vvord vvhich is heere vſed is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and anſvvereth to the Hebrevv vvord <hi>Chirma.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Significations of the Hebrew Chirma.</note> It is very emphaticall, and it is eſpecially taken vp in theſe three caſes. Firſt, vvhen a man doth a thing vvithout hope of the leaſt profit. Secondly, vvhen a man doth a thing vvithout cauſe, raſhly or lightly; but this ſenſe is not heere pertinent. The third is, vvhen a man doth a thing (as vve ſpeake) vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1706:19"/> there being nothing which might moue him thereunto, but much which might perſwade with him to the contrary: and this is the ſenſe to bee followed here. For when there was nothing in vs which might procure it, nay much which might ex-aſperate the Lord againſt vs (for wee were by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his enemies) then hee ſaued vs freely of his grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this doctrine hath matter of comfort in it for vs.<note place="margin" type="runsum">It doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs.</note> For if our iuſtification did depend on our owne worth, endeauor, and holineſſe, we could not but deſpaire. Alas what are wee (poore craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wormes) that we ſhould bee of any worth in Gods ſight, before whom the ſtarres are vncleane?<note place="margin" type="runsum">Since though ſinfull and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of nothing.</note> What is our holineſſe, but as a filthy and a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous clout? and whereunto can our endeauors reach in any thing to God-ward? who can onely roule and wallow vp and downe in the filth and puddle of our corruption; in the which the more we ſtirre, the more lothſome ſtench doe wee make. But now ſince it is not in him that willeth,<note place="margin" type="runsum">Yet we may boldly accept what God doth freely offer.</note> nor in him that runneth, but in God that hath mercy, Rom. 9.16. we may boldly accept, and confidently truſt in this free grace of God, although wee be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of it. For why ſhould wee put away this great grace offered and reuealed to vs: why ſhould we not cheerfully embrace it, and reioyce in it, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince it hath appeared vnto all, and God (without reſpect of perſons) hath ſet it out to bee enioyed of the poore, baſe, low, and vnlearned, as well as of the rich, high, noble, and learned: and it is not true humility, but a ſottiſh pride, to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and iudge our ſelues vnworthy of this ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1706:20"/> whereof it hath pleaſed God (in rich mercy) to deeme vs worthy.</p>
               <p>But yet that former poynt is not cleerly on foot. For though this doe ſhew that you may bee reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt amply (though you are altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy) yet you will bee ready to obiect, that the Lord is iuſt. If hee were onely mercifull, then you would eaſily aſſent hereunto: but he is ſo mercifull, that he is iuſt alſo, and hath pronounced it an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to him, Prou. 17.15. to iuſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or to condemne the iuſt. What then (will you ſay) will become of me being a wicked wretch? and how can the Lord iuſtifie mee being ſuch an one: all this is very true. Wherefore let vs ſearch a little further. <hi>Freely of grace</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but in the redemption of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 6.</head>
               <p>Remember then this by the way, that ſo the Lord doth iuſtifie thee of grace,<note place="margin" type="runsum">We are ſo iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as that we are made truly righteous in Chriſt.</note> that he alſo maketh thee truly iuſt in Chriſt Ieſus. This (in the proofe of this doctrine) will appeare more brightly. The poynt then directly gathered is this: that wee are iuſtified in the redemption of Chriſt, or in Chriſt our redemption. Chriſt hath been at all times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to the choſen of God as their redeemer, in whoſe blood-ſhead they ſhould haue remiſſion of ſinnes.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Who hath alway been reuealed as our redeemer.</note> After the fall of our firſt parents, when they otherwiſe had fallen into the gulfe of deſpaire, hee (our eternall Prophet) gaue out the promiſe of himſelfe, that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the ſerpents head, Gen. 3.15. that is, that Chriſt (in fulneſſe of time borne of a Virgin) ſhould diſſolue (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin" type="runsum">To Adam.</note> 1. Ioh. 3.8.) the workes of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, doe away ſinne, aboliſh death; and (as <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:1706:20"/> ſpeaketh, Rom. 16.20.) tread downe Satan vnder the feet of his elect; and our firſt parents had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment of the truth hereof. For when (by the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) they ſhould haue died the death, yet in their ſacrifices (which prefigured this ſeed, this imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lambe) they perceiued the loue of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine recouered.<note place="margin" type="runsum">To Abraham, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> had the ſame promiſe of a bleſſed ſeed (in the which all the nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed) renewed to him, Geneſ. 18.18. And in all the Prophets it were eaſie to ſhew how Chriſt was preſent to the eye of the faithfull: as likewiſe how the neerer this day ſtarre was the riſing, the more euidently hee was foretold. For God was ſtill reconciling his Iſrael, <hi>viz.</hi> (his elect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iſraelites, and thoſe few that were then ſcattered among the Gentiles) vnto himſelfe in Chriſt, euen before his comming: but when once hee was exhibited, hee reconciled to himſelfe the world, that is, the great number of his elect, which was diſperſed through the world, and did conſiſt of all ſorts, degrees, and nations. All the Fathers had Chriſt <hi>de iure,</hi> of right, though <hi>de facto,</hi> in deed he were not giuen in the fleſh:<note place="margin" type="runsum">And ſo embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of them.</note> and hee was euer preſent to their faith as their price of redemption, and ſo did paſſe for them in the acceptation of God. There was neuer any other name whereby men might be ſaued, he being (as it is Heb. 13.8.) the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for euer: what hee had been, he was; and what he was, he would be to eternity.</p>
               <p>But wherein doth this our righteouſneſſe ſtand?<note place="margin" type="runsum">Our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſtands in the redemption which Chriſt hath made for vs.</note> euen in our redemption which Chriſt hath wrought for vs, as the Apoſtle ſaith, that wee are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1706:21"/> iuſtified through the redemption of Chriſt. For which vnderſtand this, that God the Father hath laid all our ſinnes vpon Chriſt, that <hi>he was wounded for our ſinnes, hee was broken for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed,</hi> Iſa. 53.5.6. Hee hath taken our iniquities on him, and in his body borne them on his Croſſe, 1. Pet. 2.24. Wherefore hee which was moſt iuſt and righteous (offering himſelfe a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for our ſinnes, who are vniuſt, and bearing the puniſhment which our ſinnes deſerued) hath paid our ranſome, 1. Tim. 2.6. and redeeming vs by this meanes, is become that Lambe of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world: and thus hee being made vnrighteouſnes for vs by theſe his ſufferings: and if there were any further thing for vs to doe, doing it alſo for vs. (For he is the end of the Law, Rom. 10.4. and in him we are compleat, Coloſ. 2.10.) we are made in him the righteouſneſſe of God, 2. Cor. 5.21. Chriſt is therefore (in Ier. 23.6.) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iehouah our righteouſneſſe. <hi>Malachy</hi> calleth him the Sonne of righteouſneſſe, chap. 4. verſ. 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is firſt made vnto vs righteouſneſſe of God, and then doth make vs righteous vnto God. This doctrine hath three vſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, whereas the Lord doth ſo iuſtifie vs of grace,<note place="margin" type="runsum">It ſheweth the agreement of Gods iuſtice and mercy in our redemption.</note> that we are alſo made iuſt in the redemption of Chriſt, we may ſee and contemplate that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable myſterie, how the Lords iuſtice and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy doe kiſſe each other. There is all iuſtice vnto Chriſt, whoſe ſoule felt the anger of God in that extremity, that his body (affected heerewith) did ſweat clotty blood, who was broken euen with hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1706:21"/> torments by the hand of God for our ſinnes, and was humbled to the death of the Croſſe. There is all mercy to vs: it is mercy that the ſatisfaction of Chriſt ſhould be ours; that all that he did ſhould be accounted as done by our ſelues. It is mercy that Chriſt (himſelfe the ſatisfier) ſhould bee giuen vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.32. He hath gratified vs with his Sonne, hee hath beſtowed him freely on vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this may be a comfort to a diſtreſſed conſcience.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Jt ſheweth where we may fetch righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs.</note> For often beholding and feeling our fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and corruption that is in vs, wee are ready to think that we haue no iuſtice wherwith to ſtand and appeare before the Lord. But loe (beloued) here is righteouſneſſe enough for thee, and for me, and for the whole multitude of beleeuers: we are righteous in Chriſt our Redeemer. Yea but haply it will ſticke ſomwhat with thee how thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be righteous with an others righteouſneſſe. If a priuate man indeed ſhould die,<note place="margin" type="runsum">How anothers righteouſneſſe may iuſtifie vs.</note> hee could but ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for his owne ſinne, Gal. 6.5. Euery one in this order beareth his owne burthen. But the caſe is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with Chriſt: for he was not a meere man, but God, in nature, glory and maieſty equall with the Father; and hee being not a ſeruant, but the Sonne by nature, was ſent and made ſubiect to the Law, that he might redeeme vs which were vnder the Law, Gal. 4.4.5. And what Chriſt did or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, he did not as a priuate perſon, but as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, in the name and behalfe of Gods elect; and not of himſelfe, but as appointed therunto of God. It was not for himſelfe, but for the faithfulls ſake, that Chriſt did ſanctifie himſelfe, Ioh. 17.19. and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1706:22"/> God it is who doth make him righteouſneſſe vnto vs, 1. Cor. 1.30. It is of force amongſt men what one man doth in anothers name, chiefly where there is a common agreement that it ſhall bee ſo. And why may not it be thus in our iuſtification before God: for if the iuſtice of God preuailed ſo farre, that through the offence of one, many ſhal be dead, Rom. 5.15. much more ſhall his mercy cauſe that grace, and the gift of grace (that is righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is by one man Ieſus Chriſt) ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound vnto many. For the iuſtice of God ſerueth and miniſtreth to his mercy: as Rom. 11.32. <hi>God hath ſhut vp all vnder vnbeleefe:</hi> but to what intent doth Gods iuſtice this? that ſo they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſo? no, but that place might bee made for mercy: as it followeth, <hi>that he might haue mercy on all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, ſeeing the Lord doth make vs righteous in Chriſt his redemption,<note place="margin" type="runsum">It teacheth vs to renounce our owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> let vs abandon our owne righteouſneſſe in this caſe, counting our beſt deeds as menſtruous garments, reckoning all as droſſe and dung to winne Chriſt; that is, to be found not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe, but that which is through faith. This righteouſneſſe is not the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of meere man, but of God: and to bring ours hereunto, were as fooliſh as to helpe the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſunne, with the light of ſome ſmall ſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering candle; or to bring a drop of muddy water to a cleere chryſtall ocean.</p>
               <p>Now there remaineth one thing further to bee handled. For though a remedy againſt an infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be found out; though euery matter be knowne which concurreth to the confection: yet vnleſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1706:22"/> this be taken inwardly, or applied outwardly, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be effected: ſo (beloued) vnleſſe the grace of God the redemption of Chriſt bee laid to vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort, and receiued, all is in vaine. Then this is the queſtion (in the third place) how the remedies are to bee vſed and receiued? The anſwere to this queſtion is to be fetched out of the 25. verſe, and is contained in theſe words, <hi>by faith in his blood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 7.</head>
               <p>Which doth teach vs this doctrine, that wee are euery one to apprehend the grace of God in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Chriſt to iuſtification,<note place="margin" type="runsum">We are tu em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſts redemption wrought for vs by faith.</note> by hearty and vnfained faith. Faith hath been alwaies requiſite as the inſtrument to take Chriſt our righteouſneſſe, that ſo we might (in Gods ſight) be iuſtified. This is taught vs euery where, Gal. 3.22. The Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne, that the promiſe (by the ſaith of Ieſus Chriſt) ſhould bee giuen to all. And Ioh. 3.16. <hi>So God loued the world, that hee hath giuen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth on him ſhould haue euerlaſting life.</hi> Where we ſee faith to be brought in as the inſtrument with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which neither the promiſe can bee appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated, nor ſaluation attained. So Act. 16.30.31.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Which is the inſtrument to receiue it.</note> when the queſtion is made, <hi>what ſhall I doe to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> it is anſwered by the Apoſtle, <hi>beleeue on the Lord Ieſus, thou and thy houſhold, and you ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> And truly the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt hath not been of more ancient time giuen to men, than faith hath beene appointed the receiuer heereof. Wherefore it is called the righteouſneſſe of faith, becauſe it is receiued by faith, as our righteouſnes which God imputeth to vs. If we ſhould ſearch the regiſter of the Scriptures, a cloud of witneſſes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1706:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1706:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1706:24"/> would compaſſe vs about for the confirmation of this poynt. But by the way it ſeemeth more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to anſwere what may be obiected. For aboue we haue taught (you will ſay) that the grace of God cannot ſtand with any thing in man: How then (will you aske) can it ſtand with faith?<note place="margin" type="runsum">How Gods free grace doth ſtand with faith.</note> It is true that the grace of God doth not brooke any thing inherent in man, and of man, and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding may well agree with faith: for faith is not of man, no not in man by nature. For al men haue not faith, 2. Theſ. 3.2. but it is in man renewed, and as a gift of meere grace: as Phil. 1.29. <hi>Vnto you it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for Chriſt, that you ſhould beleeue on him:</hi> where faith is challenged as a largeſſe of the Lords libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Secondly, faith doth not iuſtifie vs as it is an inherent quality in vs (for this ſmelleth ſomewhat of the Gnoſticks) but as it apprehendeth Chriſt Ieſus the redeemer, who is made vnto vs of God righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Thus then briefly you ſee how euery one of vs muſt (through faith) take hold of the grace of God in the redemption of Chriſt; and that faith is not at all preiudiciall to Gods fauour. And now (me thinkes) you are willing to know what it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue?<note place="margin" type="runsum">What it is to beleeue.</note> I will tell you (and that according as the Scripture ſpeaketh) without any laborious diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. If then (beloued) you firſt hauing a ſight and ſenſe of your miſerable eſtate, and beholding Chriſt crucified before you in this Goſpell;<note place="margin" type="runsum">
                     <hi>viz.</hi> Out of a ſenſe of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery to goe and to reſt on Chriſt for our ſaluation.</note> that is, hearing the word of this free grace of God through the redemption of Chriſt, doe come and caſt your ſelues on his mercy in Chriſt the redeemer, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it into your hearts, afterward abhorring your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1706:24"/> ſelfe more and more euen in duſt and aſhes, louing this God who is ſo gracious to you, and expreſſing it by walking in his commandements; then doe you truly beleeue. For (in the ſight and ſenſe of miſery) thus to come to, and relie on Gods mercy, is to beleeue as <hi>Iohn,</hi> chap. 6. verſ. 35. <hi>Hee that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto me ſhall not hunger; and hee that beleeueth in me ſhall not thirſt.</hi> Marke heere, that to beleeue in Chriſt, and to come to him are put for one: when then our will doth moue toward God, and make vnto his grace in Chriſt, then we beleeue.</p>
               <p>Againe, to receiue the grace of God in Chriſt,<note place="margin" type="runsum">And to apply his grace to our ſelues in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</note> euen euery one for himſelfe particularly with an honeſt heart, in ſuch manner as to ſay, It is mine, it belongeth vnto me: this (by the interpretation of the Scripture) is to beleeue, Ioh. 1.12. And hee that commeth thus to Chriſt, and layeth hold on him, though it be waueringly, yet hee truly belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.<note place="margin" type="runsum">Though it be weakly and not without doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> For true faith is not alwaies an vndoubted certainty which cauſeth one gloriouſly to triumph, let the wind lie in what corner it pleaſeth: but it is ſometimes as ſmoking flaxe, and ſtandeth rather in groanes, ſighes and deſires, than confident defian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and challenges, eſpecially vnder the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of our conuerſion, and time oftentation. We ſpeake indeed againſt the popiſh doubtings, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerings, and vncertainty: firſt, to ſhew that theſe, though they may ſtand with faith, yet they are no vertues, but fruits of vnbeleefe. Secondly, becauſe that true faith, which is ſometime plunged and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed with much doubting, doth often get vp, and is carried with a ful ſaile in the perſwaſion of Gods mercy: as it is reported of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Rom. 4.20.21.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1706:25"/> that hee did not doubt of the promiſe of God through vnbeleefe, but was fully aſſured of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof: which pitch though we cannot riſe and reach vnto; yet if wee doe from the heart long after Gods grace in Chriſt, and truly (though in much weakneſſe) reſt on him for pardon of our ſinnes, there is no doubt but we haue that faith vnfained, which doth make vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that redemption which is in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1706:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
